DAN KLEIN: All right, so how
well does this thing work?
Well, if you start with a random
initial state for the n-queens
problem, then it turns out in basically
constant time with high
probability, you're going to solve it.
So before, we were talking about with
ordering, maybe we can do 25 queens.
Maybe with filtering we
can do 1,000 queens.
Well, here we can do like 10 million
queens more or less instantly with
iterate improvement.
Why?
Because it's mostly OK in
a random assignment.
We fix up the problems, and they're
relatively local for
that particular problem.
And this actually seems to be true
for any randomly generated CSPs.
So if you randomly generate a CSP,
unless you get a particularly bad
instance, then you're basically going
to solve it nearly instantaneously
with this iterate improvement
min-conflict approach.
So how does that work exactly?
Well, there are hard instances.
Why are there hard instances?
Well, you can take your CSP and
look at two quantities.
You look at how many constraints there
are and how many variables there are.
And if, for the number of variables
you have, you have very, very few
constraints, is the CSP going
to be easy or hard?
It's going to be easy.
You barely have any constraints.
You have all these variables and
they can do whatever they want.
You'll solve it almost instantly
with iterative improvement.
What happens if you have absolutely
tons of constraints?
Well, it actually turns out you might
think, OK, it's going to be really,
really hard.
Typically, if you have tons of
constraints, there actually aren't
going to be solutions, but if there
are solutions, everything is so
constrained that you just kind of chase
those solutions down through the
constraints very easily.
So if there's either very few
constraints or very many constraints,
you're great.
There's a magical critical ratio where
if you look at this ratio of
constraints to variables, there's some
critical value where things suddenly
get really, really hard because it's
just constrained enough and just free
enough that you have to do all this work
only to find that it just barely
doesn't work out.
OK.
So this seems great.
We've got this algorithm, which almost
always solves huge CSPs instantly, and
there's only this tiny little
area that's scary.
Right.
So here's the land of CSPs.
It's almost all beautiful green
pastures, but you've got this small
area of scary volcano land.
OK.
what are those volcanoes?
That's what the hard problems are.
So what's the problem?
You've got your problem, and your
problem, well, it's probably not
randomly generated.
So guess what?
You're there too.
OK.
Basically, naturally occurring problems
are going to be harder than a
randomly generated one.
It is, however, still the case that
min-conflicts and iterative
improvement are very powerful in
practice, and they're very important
techniques for solving large CSPs.